[music]
>> Between 1940 and 1945, France
experienced one of the darkest periods
in its history during the country's
occupation by the German army.
The resistance versus the collaborators,
a divide which has marked generations
ever since.
This film will explore this dramatic and
complex period
as it was experienced by the wine
producing world, a microcosm of France,
which like the rest of the country had
its heroes, its [music] villains,
and many others
who were just ordinary men and women
trying to survive as best they could.
Our story begins in the present, in
Eastern Europe, in Moldova to be
precise.
In the town of Cricova, a few kilometers
from the capital, one of the largest
wine cellars in the world can be found
storing more than a million bottles.
The kilometers of underground galleries
can be traveled by car along streets
which bear the names of outstanding
grape varieties.
In one of these rooms, 600 bottles with
an astonishing history can be found.
Here there are only classified [music]
vintages, each dating from during or
just before the Second World War.
Virtually all of these bottles of
inestimable value come from French
vineyards.
To understand how this treasure comes to
lie peacefully in the depths of this
Moldovan [music]
cellar, we need to trace its eventful
path.
During the Second World War, Nazi
dignitaries accumulated considerable
fortunes through spoliation throughout
occupied Europe.
Hitler possessed a certain number of
these great vintages, which he stocked
in the basement of his Eagle's Nest in
[music] the Bavarian Alps.
Hermann Göring amassed several thousands
of them in the cellars of Karin Hall,
his country residence near Berlin.
The German defeat [music] came in 1945.
In the Bavarian mountains, Allied troops
celebrated the capture of the Eagle's
Nest.
In its cellars, they discovered part of
the Nazi war hoard.
History doesn't tell us how many French,
Americans, and Soviets shared the
treasure.
But part of the great vintages were sent
off immediately to Moscow on Stalin's
orders,
where many were quickly consumed.
The bottles still in Cricova today are
those which escaped the father of the
nations.
In France, victory was also being
celebrated.
Bottles were brought out.
Those hidden from the Germans, as the
story goes.
At least the crowds didn't get these,
was said to be the common cry.
But the reality was less glorious.
Or in any case, more complicated.
>> Obviously, there's the legend, the
enduring myth up until the present day
of wine being hidden, the cellars
bricked up upon the arrival of the
Germans, etc., etc.
If that ever existed at all, it was very
limited and fortuitous.
Most of the time, life had to carry on.
The wine simply had to be sold. Economic
life had to continue.
Otherwise, the businesses would
disappear.
But that doesn't alter the fact that
certain wine producers
>> [clears throat]
>> helped the resistance network, hid
people, etc., as throughout French
society.
Archives of the post-war purges, and in
particular, tax archives,
show that wine merchants were probably
the most affected by the purges.
Why? Because they did a lot of trade
with Germany.
For example, we know that between 1944
and September 1945,
something like 299
very hefty fines were imposed
relating to particularly significant
profits made.
>> The historic reality of profits made
thanks to trade with the German occupier
has long gone untold.
It's still something not easily admitted
to by some of the concerned parties,
notably the numerous houses sanctioned
after the liberation.
>> In March 1946, wine merchants asked the
Commissioner of the Republic for a deal.
Sanctions imposed on them would be
hushed up.
In return for which they would pay the
fines which were, let's say,
imposed on them.
It's an important point.
>> Does that explain the unease which can
still be felt today?
>> Of course.
>> Today
80 years on
having business matters come to light.
>> Saying this trade reappears.
>> Could be embarrassing
certain houses which are still
very present on the markets.
>> Can we say which ones?
>> No.
No, because
>> Let's just say you prefer not to name
them.
Naming these houses is complicated.
Because today they could very easily
turn against the historian.
And even though a historian
might be backed up by archives,
they could be accused
of defamation
by these wine merchants.
>> 80 years after the fact, it is still
difficult to talk about a certain number
of cases in Bordeaux.
It's difficult to talk about these
things because you need a lot of courage
to do so.
Why not just admit it? Don't make waves.
Don't make waves. Don't make waves. So
and so collaborated, but we won't say
so. He collaborated. That's an end to
it.
Collaboration was rife within all the
wine merchants.
All the grand cru.
As well as in large part of the smaller
wine producers.
But even people like the wine
transporters.
The abscess has never been announced.
To understand this involvement by part
of the wine producing world, we need to
go back in time.
In June 1940, the Germans entered Paris.
An exodus had started several weeks
earlier. Millions of refugees had taken
to the roads, sometimes under fire from
German aircraft, which machine-gunned
the crowd.
They were trying to reach the free zone
in the south,
which under the terms of the armistice
signed with Germany, was to remain under
the control of the new French government
led by Philippe Pétain.
What remained of the French state
apparatus withdrew to Bordeaux, which
was occupied by German troops.
Here, confusion reigned. The city's
population went from 400,000
to nearly 1 and 1/2 million in a matter
of a few days. The mayor of the city,
[music]
Adrien Marquet, was part of Philippe
Pétain's inner circle, and he became
Pétain's minister of the interior.
He soon organized a purge, ousting from
the administration [music] anyone who
seemed unfavorable to the new regime.
He made very explicit declarations about
adhering to a German-occupied Europe.
Before the municipal council, he stated
that there was a new order and a new
reality which was German
and needed to be accepted.
It was necessary to bend to this new
reality.
So, he was part of that camp and the
epicenter of collaboration was founded
on those choices.
Bordeaux, the wine capital, was to be
deeply marked by its implication during
Adrien Marquet's term in office.
There was, of course, a no matter, a
long and drawn out of matter around all
these questions.
In Bordeaux, the large wine merchants
quickly adapted to the new situation.
Many of them were based in the Chartrons
district [music] on the left bank of the
Garonne. It's the historic district of
the major wine merchants and at the time
it was the commercial center of the
city. They were constantly careful about
staying close to the seat of power.
One of the most notorious characters in
the Chartrons world was Louis Eschauer.
He was the biggest of the city's wine
merchants, a charismatic figure from a
large Protestant Alsatian family known
to everyone as the emperor of the
Chartrons or Uncle Louis to his friends.
At the head of a colossal fortune, he
possessed several large and prestigious
[music] domains including Chateau
Compagnet and Chateau Olivier.
Florence Motte's family was very close
to the Eschauers. Her grandfather, Edme
Mongou, was the wine merchant's
right-hand man.
Here you can see the portraits of all
the Eschauers who founded the
distribution house before Louis.
Here you have the Christian Union of
young people on an outing.
This comprises all the Protestant gentry
of Bordeaux who regularly went wandering
around the local properties.
We need to understand that the
Protestant clique in Bordeaux was
basically just a little group of around
15 families.
They were all linked by their religion,
lifestyle, social status,
and also their neighborhood.
Because they all lived in the Chartrons
district.
These people lived in each other's
pockets.
They intermarried,
referred to each other as my uncle, my
cousin,
and so and so, and had a daily life of
luxury.
So, they were intermingled,
intermingled, intermingled.
>> This small community was descended from
families which had fled persecution
during the French Wars of Religion and
had taken refuge in the German
principalities. Later, some had returned
to settle in southwestern France.
These families had retained cross-border
connections, creating business links
from generation to generation, notably
in the wine trade.
>> It was very complicated. Because you see
people you know arriving with whom
you're on a first name basis.
They happen to be wearing German
uniforms, but what are you supposed to
do?
Are you going to pretend you don't know
them?
Obviously, some tried to stay a bit
aloof.
The Kressmanns pretended not to speak
German,
which made everyone laugh because they
spoke German as well as the Germans did.
But they kept pretending
that others welcomed with open arms
these people who that they considered
friends.
>> Was that the case with Louis Eschauer?
>> That was the case with Louis Eschauer.
A lot of people told him he was going
too far.
That he should be less ostentatious
about it. That walking arm in arm with a
German officer at the Bouscat race
course when the chap was in uniform was
nonsensical.
My grandmother said to him, "Listen, you
like them, you greet them, you know
them.
But tell them to come in civvies when
you invite them to dinner.
Don't have them turn up with motorcycle
outriders in their Mercedes covered in
swastikas. It's absurd.
I have no idea why he did that. It's
inexplicable.
If not for the fact that he was Louis
Eschauer,
the emperor of the Chartrons, and he
could do what he liked.
>> For Eschauer, as for all the wine
merchants of the Chartrons, the arrival
of the Germans was a godsend.
When the occupation began, the wine
producing world was in crisis. The
French economy still hadn't recovered
from the Great Depression of the 1930s.
Wine merchants had significant
quantities of unsold stock, which they
didn't know what to do with. The arrival
of the Germans represented the
possibility of stock clearance,
especially since Germany wished to
procure considerable amounts.
In this photo, Louis Eschauer poses with
one of his regular commercial partners,
the German Heinz Böhmer.
The two men had known each other for
years. Böhmer's father had himself had
business dealings with the Eschauer
house.
Luckily enough for Uncle Louis, Böhmer,
now a high-ranking officer in the
Wehrmacht, had just been put in charge
of all Bordeaux purchases for Germany.
When Böhmer was at home, there was open
house for dinner guests.
But at the same time, the Germans were
completely at home in Avenue Émile
Counord.
The attitude amongst wine merchants in
Bordeaux was, "Don't look a gift horse
in the mouth." So long as the Germans
were good clients.
And they bought just about anything.
That's the other point.
There was a certain quota of wine which
was reserved for general supplies.
And there was also more
These needed to be sold.
So they sold them.
>> Germany considered French wine as a
strategic resource.
There were wines for everyday
consumption, which were in constant
supply and essential for morale within
the ranks.
And there were classified wines for the
regime's dignitaries.
But contrary to popular and enduring
belief, the Germans didn't actually
steal the French wine production. Apart
from a few cases of theft, notably by
Göring, they actually bought it. And at
a rather good price.
>> When he arrived, Böhmers received quite
a warm welcome. He was warmly welcomed
by companies in the château. He was
warmly welcomed by the Bordeaux wine
chain. Because after all, he was very
well known.
There was a certain continuity to
It was a good opening for a certain
number of wine merchants.
>> The wine brokering house of Heinz
Böhmers, the wine führer for the
Bordeaux region, still exists today. Its
head office is in Bremen in northern
Germany.
Michael Böhmers is the son of Heinz
Böhmers. When his father died, he took
over the family business with his
brothers.
A few years ago, they decided to donate
the company's archives to the
municipality.
>> This is a note in which he precisely
describes his function.
He explains the rules concerning
quantities and prices, etc.
They're meticulously defined.
Prices were fixed at the official level.
More above.
Above above above the official price.
It seems there was a certain margin for
negotiation.
That's what my father says here.
And it coincides with my personal
experience when I went to Bordeaux in
the 1960s.
Nobody ever criticized me.
Perhaps they were being polite.
But all the same.
>> [music]
>> Perhaps they'd made a lot of money.
>> [sighs]
>> That's very possible.
At the beginning of the war, I was a
year old.
There's a short family film in which my
twin sister and myself
were celebrating our first birthday.
That was 2 days before the beginning of
that terrible war.
2 days.
My parents were not at all Nazis.
But my father nonetheless collaborated
with them.
It was necessary for his company.
He always said.
I [clears throat] tried everything in
order to work and protect my family
and carry out my duties in Bordeaux
in a civilized way as possible.
But he hadn't [music] resisted this.
If he hadn't, it's unlikely he would
have been posted to Bordeaux.
Professionally, it was a very good
period for him. Certainly not for the
French because but they were occupied.
But what about business?
I think in terms of business, they were
happy.
It was a continuation at a slightly
different level because
the quality is greatly increased.
Heims Heims Baum launched the tendering
process 11 times during the occupation.
11 tenders open to all comers for
important quantities of wine
paid for thanks to the daily indemnity
given by the Vichy regime to the German
occupier to cover occupation expenses.
11 tenders giving brokers two possible
solutions.
Do I make a proposition
or do I abstain? If I abstain, I keep my
wine. I have no money.
I can't pay my 30 employees.
So instead of feeling sorry for myself,
I face reality.
The reality is I need to clear my
stocks.
My business needs to continue.
Money needs to come in
and I have a mouth-watering opportunity.
All the major families and others
participated made propositions.
And to my knowledge,
there were no traders, no brokers
who put up any resistance to this
system.
>> Since the armistice in June 1940, France
had been cut in two. A demarcation line
had been drawn between the northern zone
occupied by Germany and the southern
so-called free zone over which the Vichy
government had authority.
>> There was a border which began at
Switzerland
and ended at Spain
with a large 90° arc close to Tours.
All the major French wine producers
found themselves under German control.
Whether they be in Burgundy or a whole
part of Burgundy was in the occupied
zone.
Champagne was of course in the occupied
zone, as were some of the wines in the
center-west. And here in Bordeaux, you
can see that the major appellations were
under German authority.
The demarcation line followed the road.
And this demarcation line represented a
real internal border.
An artificial frontier which divided
several regions in two.
In the legal definition by the occupier,
it wasn't actually a simple line.
It was a zone. A zone a few meters wide
which the Germans could distort slightly
as they saw fit. Sainte-Foy-la-Grande is
a small village which in June 1940 was
right on the demarcation line. It was
split by this internal frontier, this
artificial
At the outset of the day, cooperative
which you see here
was in the free zone.
But a few weeks, a few months later
after the Germans arrived
the demarcation line
and this cooperative ended up in the
occupied zone.
It's a small quality wine. It's a
Bordeaux vineyard. So, it was
interesting for the Germans.
>> We head northeast towards Champagne,
towards the vineyards around Épernay and
Reims.
These lands were also in the occupied
zone. The Germans had been very careful
to include them when drawing the
demarcation line.
As with the other viticulture [music]
regions, the German authorities named a
wine führer responsible for purchases
throughout the region.
In this case, it was Otto Klébish. Once
again, the Germans had been careful to
name a connoisseur of the French market.
[music]
Klébish spoke perfect French. He was
born in Cognac where his father had a
vineyard.
But that's not the only reason he was
chosen. His brother-in-law was no other
than Hitler's Minister for Foreign
Affairs, Otto von Ribbentrop.
He knew the wine sector in the Champagne
region inside [music] out.
Before becoming a Nazi minister and
eventually a war criminal [music]
executed in Nuremberg, Ribbentrop had
been the German representative for the
Mumm and Pommery Champagne houses.
So, it was directly from the Minister
[music] of Foreign Affairs that Klébish
received a briefing before leaving for
Reims.
>> What was asked of him was to be
extremely diplomatic
and to explain to the people with whom
he was dealing as his interlocutor that
if they supplied the required number of
bottles
then everything would go smoothly.
On the other hand, if things went out of
control, if spoken agreements were not
honored, they could expect reprisals to
be put in place.
So, this was the common interest at that
time.
If they could find a way of working
together while avoiding any new dramas
or new difficulties,
it could result in something very
interesting.
But the very notion of common interest
with the Germans of which you speak was
nonetheless problematic.
The interest, at least as it was
experienced here, was to accept
that if they could establish a trading
system which worked,
that meant that the population could be
peaceful.
The personnel working for the large
houses would have a salary
and could feed their families.
That may be difficult to hear,
but it was the case.
It meant avoiding new dramas like those
already experienced.
Nobody refused?
I don't very well see how they could
possibly have refused.
>> In accordance with guidelines from
Berlin, Klebisch, the wine führer for
the Champagne region, very quickly began
coaxing the profession with large orders
for Germany.
These orders were all the more welcome
because the sector was going through a
serious overproduction crisis, like the
country's other major wine producers at
the time.
At the headquarters of of CIVC, the
organization which regulated the
profession. Most archive documents
concerning these dark years
>> [music]
>> have disappeared.
But thanks to the work of one
conscientious archivist, [music]
three boxes have been preserved.
These documents are proof of business
carried out with the occupier by nearly
all the major wine producers in
Champagne.
Amongst these archives, one document is
of particular [music] interest. It was
written by the head of the CIVC,
Robert Jean de Vogüé, and singles out
the houses which sold much more than the
others to the Germans.
It was important for de Vogüé that all
the houses should have an equal share in
this new opportunity provided by the
occupier.
Demand was clearly very high. Orders
needed to be fulfilled for the German
market to supply soldiers stationed all
around Europe,
but also to satisfy the social needs of
high-ranking members of the Reich,
for whom French Champagne now had the
taste of victory.
At the Ritz in Paris, German officers
and prominent figures of the
collaboration, such as the Marquis
Melchior de Polignac, the director of
Pommery, regularly met.
At the time, Polignac was one of the
leaders of the collaboration group,
which openly campaigned for a
German-occupied Europe.
In Épernay, it was decided to delete
this painful memory. The former park of
the Pommery house is today a public
garden, and the bust to the glory of its
former head has conveniently
disappeared.
Here, as in Bordeaux, they prefer not to
keep reminders of this embarrassing
past.
Although the attitude of Polignac didn't
reflect that of all the houses, another
cumbersome character also tarnished the
history of Champagne under the
occupation,
René Bousquet.
This was the man who in 1942 organized
the largest mass arrest of Jews in
France, the Vel' d'Hiv Roundup, which
led more than 13,000 people to the death
camps.
At this time, he was prefect of the
Marne. It was with his backing, a year
before the roundup, that the CIVC had
been created.
>> What was the role of Rene Bousquet in
this affair?
>> As
I have said, the prefect of the Marne
had always held talks with wine
producers and brokers who named him the
prefect of Champagne.
So, the prefect of the Marne was the
direct contact and even the advocate of
professionals at a governmental level.
Bousquet spent very little time in
Champagne. He was nominated in 1940.
After that, he moved to the national
spheres. He disappeared.
Bousquet defended the interests of the
Champagne region against the pretensions
and the prerogatives of the occupation
authorities.
>> Is it possible to separate that from the
overall image of the person?
>> It's not connected.
They were two different periods of life.
It's not because Bousquet became
what he later was
that that smears the creation of the
CIVC.
The CIVC.
It's not connected.
>> The Champagne region is a good example
of the ambiguities within the wine
producing world towards the Germans.
On one hand, the profession easily came
to terms with the German presence, even
profited off it. On the other hand, it
counted a certain number of resistance
within its ranks.
And its good relationship with the
Wehrmacht helped protect others. Some
within the profession were already
resistance in 1940. Others, initially
loyal to Vichy, gradually changed sides,
particularly when German demands
increased. This was the case with Robert
Jean de Vogüé, the profession's
principal representative.
As of 1943, there was a clear stiffening
on the German side.
Agreements between de Vogüé and the wine
Führer Klebisch were no longer
respected.
The Germans now seem to want to use up
all the stock of wines from Champagne.
In these minutes from a meeting at the
Majestic Hotel, the headquarters of the
German forces, it's clear that [music]
the French contingent used all possible
arguments in an attempt to reduce
deliveries.
One month later, right in the middle of
a meeting with Klebisch, Robert Jean de
Vogüé was arrested by the Gestapo.
He was condemned to death, but
eventually pardoned when Vichy
intervened.
He spent the rest of the war detained in
different German prisons until the
arrival of the Allies.
Other directors were also arrested for
showing resistance.
But despite these episodes which honor
the profession, it remains difficult to
discuss this period of history today.
None of the major Champagne houses were
prepared to participate in this film.
One of the most famous of them,
Taittinger, initially agreed before
changing its mind under the pretext that
the house was less significant under the
German occupation.
Why such a reply?
Particularly when documents prove that
Taittinger traded with the Germans
throughout the war in the same
proportions as most of the Champagne
houses.
At the time, the company was headed by
Pierre Taittinger, an ardent defender of
the Vichy regime and leader of the young
patriots far right league.
>> It's still a sensitive subject which is
rarely touched upon.
>> Does the reputation of the main houses
play a role?
>> It's true that the houses have always
taken care of their reputations.
>> But that's true of all these companies
and business enterprises.
>> There has never been a full scale
interpretation of what happened.
>> They tried to immediately pass on to
other things after the liberation.
>> This period still [music] overshadows
the French vineyards.
While some families sometimes have a
[music] selective memory, others
discover the troubled history of their
domain later on.
This was the case with Florence and
Daniel Cathiard.
In 1991, they acquired one of the most
famous domains of Bordeaux,
Château Smith-Haut-Lafitte.
It was only a few years later,
>> [music]
>> in consultation with an archivist from
the region, that they discovered part of
the history of the property which had
been hidden from them.
>> This lady told me that the château was
bought around 1905 by a brokering house
situated in Bremen. This company did a
great deal with the Bordeaux region. It
was at that time the property of the
families Böhmer and Ullrich. The Böhmer
in question was the father of Heinz
Böhmer, who during the Second World War
became the Wein-Führer for the Bordeaux
vineyards.
>> So, Heinz Böhmer, the officer who
reigned over Bordeaux on behalf of the
Reich, had owned, thanks to his father,
the Château Smith-Haut-Lafitte.
But another name reappeared during
Florence Cathiard's research,
that of the unavoidable Louis Eschauer,
the most compromised [music] trader
during the German occupation, who
managed the domain for Boermans before
buying it a few years later.
>> We didn't have the historical background
because we weren't born into a Bordeaux
family.
If you look at my archives
and I have quite a bundle of them, it's
mentioned on two pages. That's all.
It was a surprise.
Afterwards when we started restoration
on the Chartreuse, this is something I
can show you. We found bullet marks in
the ironwork.
I couldn't understand it. I thought
they'd fought alongside resistance.
You'll see, here it is.
It's as though the metal has melted.
You see it here?
We learned that it happened during
parties with Boermans and Esch enauer
who drank a lot with a number of
Bordeaux lay people present.
We stumbled across this because in
Bordeaux it was something of an amateur
at the time.
It's a way to have conversations
conversations in Bordeaux in any case.
I know about this through the wine court
and the aristocracy of which I'm now a
part thanks to Smith Haut Lafitte.
We don't have that sort of conversation.
We don't feel a duty to remember.
>> The few other major owners that we
approached did not wish to express
themselves in this film.
And neither did the professional
association which represents them, the
CIVB.
"In Bordeaux we look to the future." is
a sentence often heard.
Effectively looking to the past would
mean confronting for example the less
than glorious episode of the association
between Heinz Boermans, the wine führer
of Bordeaux, and Louis [music] Esch
enauer, the emperor of the Chartron.
>> Right after the German invasion in the
month of June 1940,
Esch Nauer set up a company with Bermès.
That was incredible.
He could have waited 3 months, 6 months,
a year, honestly. The next day he runs
to a solicitor to set up a shared
company.
For me, that's unpardonable.
The other thing that Louis Esche Nauer
might be accused of
is having acquired Aryanized Jewish
goods.
In particular the Château Lestage, which
belonged to the Natan family.
Obviously, that was profiting from the
situation to acquire the Medoc vintage.
Which incidentally was quite a good
wine.
That clearly doesn't play in his favor.
>> From the autumn of 1940, Germany began
organized spoliation [music] of goods
belonging to Jews in the occupied zone,
as they did throughout Europe.
This policy was taken up by the Vichy
government,
which in 1941 set up a Commissariat
General for Jewish Affairs. [music]
The Germans had their eye on certain
reputed domains, like that of the
Rothschild family,
but in the end Vichy took their vines.
The owners were stripped of their French
nationality.
As for Louis Esche Nauer and Heinz
Bermès, they were on the lookout. A
neighbor had just announced Natan, owner
of the Château Lestage domain, to the
Commissariat for Jewish Affairs.
Learning that the property was on the
point of being confiscated, Esche Nauer
and Bermès suggested to Natan that they
purchase it at a low price before its
seizure. Obliged [music] to take flight,
the Natan family could not refuse their
offer.
>> Going through the family home's
archives, Michael Burmester came across
a trace of this dubious transaction from
which his father and Louis Eschauer
profited. The document confirms the sale
without mentioning the debatable
conditions.
>> After the war, he visited Listrac.
He didn't mention the case to the owner
of the time.
It might result in expropriation or
something of that sort.
So,
I
have absolutely no idea how my father
came to be owner of the Chateau Listrac.
>> Knowing your father, would it have
concerned him to take advantage of a
cheap purchase from a Jewish family?
>> I don't think my father
was someone who would have sacrificed a
good opportunity.
If he thought
somebody else would step in and
do the same thing.
I can't imagine him
reacting a bit like that.
Obviously,
it's not pleasant for me to imagine that
my father could have reacted in that
way.
But I cannot exclude it.
>> The 2nd of February, 1943.
On the other side of Europe, German
troops experienced their first major
defeat at Stalingrad.
The war was gradually turning in the
allies favor.
In France, part of the wine cork
nobility was still living it up.
Unaware that the tide was turning.
It was to take long months of battle
before the first French towns took up
arms against the occupier.
As the allies and the troops of General
de Lattre de Tassigny advanced.
After a week of fighting, Paris was
liberated on the 25th of August 1944.
Reims in the Champagne region were
liberated a few days later.
As for Bordeaux, the city was liberated
by the end of August. But there was no
fighting in Bordeaux, which owed its
liberation to an agreement between the
German authorities and the resistance
fighters.
The mayor of the city, Adrien Marquet,
as well as Louis Eschauer, appear to
have played an important role in this
agreement.
Notably, [music] thanks to the close
relationship between Eschauer and one of
the high-ranking officers, Ernst
Kuhnemann, himself a wine trader in
civilian life.
>> Even when the final liberation came
about
the wine producing world would
once again
one more time play a role which would be
widely remembered.
Because what do we recall of the events
today?
The action of Adrien Marquet and the
action of Louis Eschauer
because the liberation of Bordeaux boils
down to two stages,
the Germans leaving then the FFI
arriving.
>> [music]
>> There was no contact between them.
>> Does that also go to explain why both
Marquet and Eschauer remain relatively
esteemed characters?
>> Yes, in the end it was a peaceful
liberation.
The different actors present in Bordeaux
the wine producing world
Adrien Marquet
were already watching their backs. We're
already preparing what was to come.
>> Once the Germans had left the city, the
settling of accounts began.
The net began tightening around war
profiteers of all kinds, around
collaborators [music]
suspected or proven.
Within the wine world a certain number
of people were preparing for difficult
times.
Louis Eschauer was quickly arrested by
the liberation forces and held at the
Fort du Hâ
in the very place where the Germans had
interned resistance.
Ironically his co-detainee with whom he
shared a cell was none other than the
mayor of Bordeaux, [music]
Adrien Marquet.
In the summer of 1945, Germany
capitulated.
As with a large number of German
officers present in Bordeaux, Heinz
Böhmer managed to leave the country
unhindered.
Bremen, the city of his birth, had taken
a pounding from the allies.
>> My father had always thought that
Germany would be defeated.
It did not surprise him.
He called it absolute madness.
Because
the war would certainly be lost.
In any case, it was a huge error,
whichever way you look at it.
There's a folder
with a whole list of my father's
associates,
acquaintances,
were accused of collaboration.
I think it was written by Madame
Eschauer.
And it must have been in 1947.
In my opinion,
it was a list which my father had asked
for to find out the fate of his friends
and acquaintances in Bordeaux.
Eschenauer spent 18 months in prison,
sentenced to 4 years, but freed after 18
months.
Goods probably confiscated.
Married Jean,
in good health,
now living in Paris.
Descas, 13 months in an internment camp,
now carries on business as usual.
Petri Marty, I think I met this
gentleman. Large fine, little
inconvenience.
Large fine is nonetheless inconvenient.
>> In fact, all your father's friends had
problems after the war.
>> Yes, not all of them, but a good number.
>> In the archives of the Burmes house, the
name of a woman appears, Gertrude
Kircher, nee Villute. She was the
assistant of Heinz Bormann in Bordeaux.
But unlike Bormann, who managed to
return to Germany, Gertrud Kiescher was
arrested at the time of the liberation
in Bordeaux.
Interrogated by the free French
intelligence services, she claimed to be
in possession of precious archives
>> [music]
>> concerning the most visible characters
in the Bordeaux wine business.
>> He told me that he had had all the
documents destroyed.
Perhaps he gave the order, but it wasn't
carried out. Perhaps what I don't know.
>> We've uncovered the transcript of
Gertrud Kiescher's interrogation. It is
edifying.
Gilbert Woah, 7 Rue Henri Colignon,
>> [music]
>> very sympathetic towards Germany.
Flouret, Avenue Emile Counord,
Germanophile.
Calvet, father, numerous sales
propositions, friendly relationship with
Bormann, received at his house.
Eschenauer, Germanophile, invited German
generals to dinner.
Kruse, Germanophile, very friendly
relationship with Bormann.
Descas, informed Bormann of anyone who
undermined Franco-German economic
agreements.
To the point of personally dictating
letters to the authorities.
In exchange for this information, a
veritable who's who of the collaboration
[music] network in Bordeaux,
Gertrud Kiescher was given a new
identity by [music] the French
intelligence service,
under which she was to be confined to
her residence for a while before
disappearing without a trace to this
[music] day.
Louis Eschenauer was given a fine of 105
million francs, the equivalent of 10
million euros. His goods were
confiscated.
Other prominent names in Bordeaux were
sentenced, such as the Cruse, Descazes,
Labory, D'Estournel, Barton & Guestier,
and the large houses.
The agreement that was made with the new
authorities, quick payment of fines in
return for no publicity about sanctions,
[music]
was so well respected that 80 years
later, the secret is still jealously
guarded.
In the Champagne region, a report
[music] published in September 1944
qualifies certain fortunes amassed
through trade with the occupier as
scandalous. [music]
But 1 year later, the follow-up was
minimal.
Only two [music] figures from Champagne
were convicted, Lucien Drouin
and Melchior de Polignac, the head of
Pommery.
The legal network reformed quickly after
the war, helping to bury a certain
number of inquiries.
The large majority of houses were able
to continue doing business peacefully.
>> What happened after the war?
Your father finally returned to France,
if I understand correctly.
>> Yes.
>> Carrying on business with the same
people?
>> The same The same people. I mean,
practically the same.
The same vendors and buyers, etc. Yes.
I know that my brother,
who was 12 years older than myself,
went on a long trip in 1950.
During which
he visited all the acquaintances in
France.
Not just in Bordeaux.
And he was welcomed everywhere with open
arms.
>> Business continues.
Several houses called into question in
this film still exist today.
With a few rare exceptions, they still
refuse to discuss the German occupation
period or allow unrestricted access to
their archives, thus depriving
historians of precious information for
continued reflection on this crucial
period of history.
>> L'image est négative.
>> It gives a negative image when you're at
the head of a renowned commercial
enterprise.
You don't want negative publicity when
you're in that situation.
It's easy to understand.
But this part of the Second World War
has remained untouched.
Nothing has yet been expurgated.
In fact, we don't consider it anymore.
But the problem's still there. So it
will resurface.
It will resurface.
The story isn't over.
It carries on [music] within us.
Despite the disappearance of those
directly connected and the desire of
certain people to smother it,
it is now the essential task of their
descendants
>> [music]
>> to draw the lessons from this part of
French collective history.
>> Mhm.